Ooh, even a camera. I'm impressed.
Sure.
On tablet.
That's true.
No. In the first time, see.
Right.
So today we start.
Digging down so far,
we spent most of the time talking about
programming languages.
None.
Because T to enter all the programming
language, all the instructions,
all these elements are basically there to.
Understand.
A programme not just by looking, you know,
at the simple constructs,
but to have a full understanding of the
implications of any single punctuation,
comma, semi colon or whatever in your.
In in a in a programme that you wrote,
or more likely that has been generated.
Just to give you an example,
I just accepted the the first automatic
pull request from.
From BAI in one of the official system of
University of Peace,
so it is official that there was a bad
fix entirely produced by the I I posed
the question. Of course I review.
Truly the, the, the,
the the proposal changes and I was
convinced.
So I accepted the good request into the
main system so.
This is something and it I mean this one
was easy enough,
but actually it's nevertheless it's a
first. So now we start looking at how.
The runtime is implemented so this week
will be dedicated to the runtime.
Uh.
The runtime is a fairly complicated
object.
I will use the DOT net runtime in our
conversation first because I know and I
actually I even contributed to this code
base.
23 years ago,
so I know the thing in rather detail,
even though I just re browsed the full
source code. I did work to the.
net frameworkfor.
net framework from Microsoft.
Being discontinued and when they created
the.
net core version it it has been changed
and simplified to be portable so some of
things I I found some others I didn't but
nevertheless.
That was easy. Enough enough to catch up,
and the original concepts are still there.
So it's something that it's rather simple
to browse,
so this week will be dedicated to.
Several aspects. So first of all,
we will have to cope and understand how
to face a real large code base.
How can you search information inside?
How can you validate your hypothesis
without having to go through a project
that in this case?
I think it was.
3000 human years of work OK in the sense
that the original runtime has been
developed by a team of 600 people working
secretly for five years. So.
OK. And in general,
it's basically impossible for you to
understand it's it's like leaving,
I don't know in Mexico City or a Cairo,
I mean in a city that which is so large
that is basically impossible for.
A citizen to have visited every street in
that city. Nevertheless,
you still live there and the same is when
you have to maintain a code that has an
history.
So it's unlikely that you will know all
the corners of that code and and so you
have to learn how to leverage in your
knowledge about constructs,
feed programming, language features,
binding models,
etcetera so that you can go and say, OK,
I need.
To answer this question, how does it work?
The garbage collector in the in the net
and then you start with simple things and
sometimes they work.
Sometimes it's not as easy and you have
to dig down more to understand the the.
The thing but before reaching there,
I think time is ripe to spend half an
hour.
No more than that into the concept of.
Source code management,
source code management.
How many of you have used the git ends up?
How many of you have created the pull
request?
No.
Time is improving,
so I may even shrink it, but nevertheless,
for those who didn't wave the their hand
few words I think are important to say I
mean.
And.
In the 80s.
Source control was made,
so this is a first hand story.
I think it's nice because it gives you a
hand about software engineering evolution
and so during the 80s and end of the 80s
beginning of the 90s in Microsoft,
they started developing office.
Back then,
Word was a super important programme.
There was a system for for PCs that was
called Wordstar.
There was a text based editor and
Microsoft started developing the suite,
the office suite.
Back then,
they were already using network file
systems.
So basically the the rapper was on a
shared drive in the net in the local
network.
And and there was a directory source code.
And in inside there was all the officers
code and and of course all the
programmers kept writing their own piece
of code and there were no Visual Studio
code or any other idea.
Was barely the the the note panda.
So they were writing and developing the
code,
and so of course there was some
probability that some change to the part
of the code will break some other part of
the code.
So the rule of the land was that every
night.
There was one person in charge for
compiling and managing and checking that
the code base.
The code base was consistent,
which was of course an extra worker and.
If the code was broken by someone they
picked up the the guy who did break the
the code base and now became the new code
branch mountainer OK.
And so that was the way of managing code.
40 years ago.
The end of the 90s.
Source code management system became
rather popular beginning of 2000,
so the idea that the codebase is
basically a lead thing where you have.
To,
you need to be able to perform a number
of operations.
One is the the ability to freeze the
state of the code.
Branching.
So what is a branch?
OK.
And why do you think it's important to
make a a snapshot?
Certainly want the same.
You can mark a point in point in time.
And basically the the system keep tracks
of the changes so that you can go back
and forward. That's one main object,
main goal and the original.
Umm.
There,
there were a number of concurrent
revisioning system.
CVS was one of the popular and basically
the the.
The typical model was there is a main
branch.
Which is basically where the latest and
version of the software typical in
development is,
and then when a product was released,
you take a picture.
And and then there is give me one second
because this, Stefano, Stefano,
Stefano so Stefano Isabelliato.
So now let's join it will join 30 post.
Be me.
No. Yeah. See. See. Confer more epic,
you know, shuffa and picture the far.
No, no, no ****. Turn on that.
No, see.
No, that's all. No, no. Did I say that?
Bye.
Occam.
The positive.
C Sharon.
Sorry, because we have engineer. Yeah,
I have to be sure that everything's OK,
so.
Every branch was basically.
Sorry, it was the. It was.
The message was based with the AI.
Yeah. No, no, no, it wasn't. No.
The problem there was more physical,
actually.
They were installing the new firefighting
system inside the centre in engineer.
Yeah, and.
There was a a company that it was
performing the installation.
It wasn't university people and they they
ended the installation,
they did the check that is mandatory and
the check went bad in the sense that the.
File System filed and that so data centre
are complicated because.
To shut them down in case of fire is very
difficult.
So firefighting system basically there
are number approach.
The one we use use a powder that
suffocate the the the combustion thrown
at a high pressure.
So there was a leakage.
So the full teaching classroom,
etcetera were invaded by these white
smoke. Yeah, and.
That that is one part,
but the the the extra pressure basically
did break water pipe.
And and so water was popularised and
power supplied through the fan inject
ingested the water internally.
So there was a number of short circuits
and so.
It's been quite complicated and so
actually all engineering part of the
hospital,
a few other areas are without Wi-Fi
network and everything and we're trying
to restart as soon as possible,
but it's complicated.
It's happened in the days when we have
based on rain beat that much. Yeah,
that that happened in the that that day.
But basically that was only a part of the,
I mean of course that in make more things
more difficult for.
Students that evacuated the so that so no,
it it wasn't a replication,
but I can tell you some story at some
point, but not now. OK,
so basically you have the vertical branch
with all the releases, so.
And you branch the version one went to 1.
1 excel.
And that was OK, because let me pull up.
Our tragic BT friend so that I can.
Generate few interesting diagrams.
Programming.
Can you show diagram of a typical typical
no typical?
CVS evolution.
With the branches.
So originally the idea was simply being
able to track the differences. In fact,
the original source control revision
systems.
Where implemented by using Shell Commons
and a lot of the tool of diff.
Diff is a very historical tool in in
Linux that makes you have the difference
between 2 files.
And and things were OK,
but the basically the model of the CVS or
similar.
So the original source revisioning system.
We're originally designed for a single
company or a single group of developers,
not that large.
So at some point Linux was becoming an
important operating system.
And.
The model.
Which define the.
This is a typical evolution.
So you branch when you branch,
you can start from the so branch A.
If I move on the branch AI have the
source code that particular in that
particular branch,
then I can modify that particular branch
and obtain a new version in that branch
and so basically the source control looks
like a tree.
Use case use case I release version one,
there is a bug in version one.
The main branch keeps going,
so it's not any more compatible with
version one.
It's it's inconsistent possibly.
Or with bugs or whatever.
So you want to move,
you want to fix the bug in that
particular vision you create you you do
the changes, you commit the changes,
and that's the new version.
So that was the original.
Way of using these things and it was
pretty solid and continue as I was saying
Linux.
Was too complicated since the beginning.
I mean, you know,
is a project that started almost as an in
an operating system force.
So it was basically a student project to
explain how an operating system can be
implemented.
Then things get becomes serious.
It's become and it's become what we know
today. And Lena started the turbo,
which was the original author, became.
The so-called benevolent dictator,
the benevolent dictator,
is the name that is said in the open
source project,
where there is one person that.
Is recognised as the leader of the
project and he's benevolent.
He accept all the pull requests and all
the contribution from everybody.
But he decide whether to include
something or not. Dictator.
And Linux is basically still the
benevolent dictator of the Linux project.
And at some point, he said, OK, CVS,
this kind of revisioning system are
simply not enough to sustain a project
like Linux with multiple companies
contributing to the project multiple.
I mean CVS you have.
Users which are.
Basically,
in the same authentication system it's a
company sort of implementation.
Linux was like.
I mean you don't want the first
contributor to break Linux code for the
for the whole world.
So we need some new mechanism to work in
in this new world where we have too many
developers that may destroy an artefact
which is shared.
Among so many peoples so.
He set out in implementing with a number
of people,
a new system for for controlling revision.
There was more scalable and it's called
Git. OK,
and Git has become the de facto standard
today. So but it is important.
That you understand that Git is also the
most complicated of the of the control
revision source system,
because it implements operations.
I I think I can say that I.
Control maybe 30% of Git mean git is a
very complicated and for many project you
don't really use all the features that
are included.
But if I have to ask you what are the
main operation that you do?
When you use it, that's.
None.
So so a lot of.
Branch matching.
OK, that's that's a potential use of.
Of of a git in general, you have.
So when you have multiple branches just
to explain what is the problem.
When you when you start branching,
of course branches may have a common
ancestor,
and of course you're not touching all the
code base so.
If you are in this node of branch B of
branch A and and you found the bug which
in fact has been introduced in the here
before the branching,
of course this bug will affect the main
the branch A but also the branch B.
So at some point you say, OK,
but now I'm on branch A and I want to
change the the bug here,
but only this part of the bug fix I'm
making should be merged into the other
branches.
Which means basically all the changes you
made to the code are copied and merged
with other changes that already in the
meantime happened in the other branches.
Because I know that this is a common
problem, OK? And so that is a typical.
Thing that is complicated. So in general,
for instance,
CVS was having a model that was much
simpler.
You can merge changes from a bench on
into the main branch. Easy,
but this is too.
Simple for Linux because you may have a
change depending on the models in the
kernel.
Another one depending on C groups and so
how can I measure the changes and they
started introducing new concepts such as
rebase that you just.
Mentioning mentioned which helps managing
complicated managing strategies. OK,
but apart from this there is a slightly
advanced the use of git when I start.
A project don't get. What should I do?
Mm-hmm.
It in it if you're creating an empty repo
or clone typically, which is.
What does clone? What clone does?
Yeah.
So basically clone makes a copy of an
existing repository.
And beware this is important because the
clone is more than the original
initialization of a repo in CVS.
In CVS you were just say OK.
There is a server which contains all the
source code.
I want a copy of this particular branch
to work easy.
Clone is more than that because you can
take a repo which may not even be even
your repo make a local copy of that repo.
And in this respect is something that you
must become familiar with because you are
making a copy even of your own report.
So where the clones leaves leaves in your
disc.
Which is a completely different operation
than connecting it to an external server.
So your changes anything is local to your
cloned copy, so clone is.
None.
Let me see if.
Come on. Are you serious?
Hunts.
If I ask you with another,
you can replace. OK. No,
that's not the interesting part.
We will look into it after.
OK so.
Clone I start with a project I do clone,
so I create a new repository on my
machine.
So this respects the distributed nature
of the Linux kernel development.
Everyone makes a copy,
works with the copy, and then you want to.
Merge changes if someone the dictator
says OK, you can merge this. OK,
so clone after clone.
Come on.
Let's make simple operations first.
So you did clone. Now you have.
We can even do it maybe.
You you start editing the files in your
local directory stashing.
So.
Is that make the changes?
Possibly you respect the style of the
repo. If it's code that you didn't write.
So typically there are guidelines in the
project that tells you please do this,
don't do that, etcetera.
Which typically people violate
systematically, so,
OK and eventually you have a number of
useful comments. So let me.
Come online. Let me go.
Somewhere where I have.
I repo just to.
Actually.
I knew that I I wasn't born.
I was telling that it was originally born
due to the issue with the yards,
because before the the yard were made by.
So if someone wants to make a,
they have to send an e-mail with their
clients in it with changes.
Then someone who's back and forth in the
invalid support and do the revenues so
they invent.
Yeah.
This is one of the problems,
so just to let let me first show a few
comments and then we comment so.
It follows a convention that has been
basically introduced by Hadoop.
Almost 12 weeks ago of having a command.
With with the number of subcommons.
So if I say Git I get the the list of
verbs that I can use and if I say and I
have clone and in it of course.
And then I was expecting other you know.
Kind of calm answer and tell me the less
it's OK and and then you you can say.
You can collaborate with other.
You can rebase manager.
You can change your code base.
You can show you can examine this title.
So this is another big important part to
track the evolution of the software. So.
Its status for instance.
Tell me.
Look in this you have changes in in these
files that are not been yet in the repo
so.
Actors in a in a source repository are
the current directory.
That is where you make the changes.
Then there is the repository.
Which is where all the branches and
everything are stored. When you clone you,
you're cloning the repository, you're not.
Simply copying the current version. OK,
so you are creating a new repository on
your machine and then all the operation
on the source code.
If you create the the the branch,
that branch leaves on your machine.
If you create a file you if you are the
new file to the repository that files
goes into.
To the in in that local repository.
And because of this cloning,
at some point it's OK,
but I did some useful work to the Linux
kernel.
I want to match these changes into the
real repository,
not into my local repository.
So at some point, a number of.
Operations have been introduced between
repositories,
so if you if a repository is a clone of
another repository then you can use
specific command to.
Make some align operations from one to
the other. So first of all,
Git is not simply dedicated to manage the
source code,
but basically is an organic model in
which you have multiple repository that
have a relation between them. So actually.
The repository knows from which it was
Clonated cloned and and then through the
comments you can not only change your
repository but also related repository.
Using mechanisms that are called full
requests.
OK,
but before digging into the notion of the
pull request,
which is an interesting notion,
let's keep looking at this.
So status is a typical.
Common new issue that shows you the files
that you've changed it and are not yet
committed to the repository.
So the typical operations are checkout.
In CVS it was called checkout because
there was no clone.
So you did check out an existing source.
You have a local copy.
You modify the files of that local copy,
and then you want to commit your changes
back into the repository.
The source the the source revision system.
Cheques,
whether the files have changed in the
meantime.
Because if you imagine there are multiple
developers,
these multiple developers keep changing
the files so some conflict may arise.
And there are several kind of conflicts.
One is you added a different portion of
the file, which is OK,
so I can manage the sections and the code
may become inconsistent because of this
merging or.
To developers edit exactly the same line
of the same file.
That's a conflict that you have to
resolve manually,
and so the system says no, no, no.
I'm sorry I can't commit until you
resolve this conflict for me.
And you have to fix some.
And typically you get some support that
shows that.
The the different alternatives to to
choose from,
and that is the typical life cycle.
So you add files to the repo,
all the files that have not been
explicitly added to the.
So if I create a file not upon full dot
TXT in this directory, so I created the.
The now I say need status.
And I have school that has been added to
the untracked files.
So if you create a file which is not part
of the repository,
the system understands it and say OK,
sorry, this is untracked.
So you want you want to meet.
That I track the changes also to this
file because it becomes part of the
repository pressed operation.
You have to say add to the. Oh,
that's interesting.
It add.
Scores and EJ.
Sample election this should be added. OK,
so now it status.
I have now the modified files.
The new file added to the repository,
so the repository is not yet populated
with the file and untracked files.
Now I cannot say I want to commit.
OK, commit.
Typically they say don't commit all
because when you commit you also have to
provide some description of what you're
committing.
Umm.
So sort of is that source region.
Yes,
sample that action so I can explicitly
commit the file.
Now I get an inline editor, hopefully.
There we are and I can say.
As you can see,
there are changes to be committed.
Change it not staged for commit,
so this will not be committed into the
repo.
So after this operation only sample
election SQL will be.
I did that.
Sample sequel.
Script to create the BB with the sample
election for.
Uh.
Testing bar *******.
Here we are.
Now.
I write and inside the local repository.
Hmm.
That's interesting.
In those.
Invite bright operation.
No, this is, yeah. And we are able.
So if I, I suspect what is the problem,
but I'm I'm not gonna.
I'm not absolutely.
Hmm.
Oops.
OK.
Secret file to.
Create an index sample.
Yeah.
Sample election.
Oh, I don't know what I did click, sorry.
For texting or.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
Ah.
What's the compass?
What is the Iraq which is?
It's me.
Yeah.
OK.
Of sequel script.
To create a sample action for testing
purposes.
Right.
OK, the status.
Now the the file has been added to the
repository and it's not change it,
so there are no changes if I.
Note but the.
If I edit that file.
OK, so this is.
I simply add the a single.
Thing.
This sample action now is in the modified
files.
The system is smart enough that if it's
not using just the date of the change.
So I removed the change and as you can
see now.
The there is no more like the sample
election sequel in the list because is it
equivalent to the the the version that
you have in the repository? OK so.
This is the basic cycle.
I obtain I have a repository,
I check out some,
some somehow the source code.
This may happen by cloning in the gate or
check by making check out in other
systems. Nevertheless,
I have a repository and.
The directory with the current files I
work on the files and then using a number
of commands I update the repo.
The repo is the one who is shared across
multiple developers in the Git.
Reality is that the repo you're working
in is.
Your own because when you clone,
you have a local copy of the full
repository.
Then you use operation between
repositories to align everything OK and
so the typically.
The typical operations that you perform
are.
Pull and push. So pull is.
I wanna take all the changes from the
original repository of which this is a
clone and I won't wanna bring all the
changes.
In into my local copy or push which is I
want to synchronise this repository with
the remote repository.
Both operations assume that you are the
owner.
Of the the repository.
If you're not the owner of the source
repository,
then clearly you can't pull into that.
It's not yours, so you're you.
You get an error then in that case you
can create a pull request.
So you say, OK, I am,
I have cloned cloned your repository.
My version is better than yours I think.
Please take all my changes in this pull
request.
And so basically make a pool.
So in usually when you when you use it in
the very simple way git.
You clone your,
you create your repository on GitHub,
let's say OK or in any other git system.
GitHub is one of the most popular.
So let's say GitHub.
You create your repository on GitHub even.
On the web, not even writing anything. OK,
then you clone the repository you work on
the repository and you pull your change.
You can meet locally and you pull changes.
That's the normal work workflow.
When you create a pull request,
basically you are in inverting the source
and the destination.
So basically say hey I clone for you.
Can you pull from me?
OK,
so you're switching the roles in the two
repository.
I want you to pull these changes into
mine. OK, let's try to see this.
Let me switch to another more simple
repository.
OK.
Hmm.
There are a number.
Uh.
OK.
So this is the graphical rendering of
course of the pool request. OK so.
Actually.
This is the one I created the using
charge PT so that's.
And if I click here,
I can review the changes OK.
So in this case it's a very basic change,
which is I want to add the line this line
to insert this assignment that was not
there before, OK.
Of course the the pull request in this
particular example that is very simple.
So you may say oh,
you use ABI to add one line of code. Yes,
because the problem wasn't adding the
line of code, but.
I did use the AI to double check if my
memories about the code,
the repo that I developed so I know it.
We're right because I want to try to fix
a bug, but I wasn't sure of the same.
Fix of that particular field.
So I had some conversation with AI asking
questions about where it is used and can
I, etcetera, etcetera.
So I did all the analysis and mix it with
AI and eventually she proposed me.
You can fix it like this and review the
code that commits.
And then say OK,
create the pull request and then I merged
the pull request inside the the repo.
So in this case the AI cloned the
repository, the AI is not owner.
Of the repository so created the pull
request on the repository.
I asked the owner of the repository.
I accepted to pull those particular
changes to my repository OK and so now
this is part.
Of the the thing and of course the the
code become weekly a three.
None.
Let me check.
Hmm.
I don't want to going in into this
business.
Because basically three that I can browse
and see all the various changes,
I can try to use the UI or.
Other means to select the branch.
To select.
The bed is so this branch is old is 4
years old.
This is another three years old Branch,
and as you can see there are active
branches.
That recently we use a leisure at
University of Calabria for electing
director.
So we we did some release branches to
ensure that everything was was OK.
And pull request and then of course you
can go and browse the branch and in this
case you you.
I'm looking at the source code as it was
when I did the the the branch. OK,
so conceptually it's fairly.
Nice and easy,
but it's something that I'm happy that
most of the class using this mechanism
because it is.
It's a good way to work and it will
become more and more important.
Uh.
With the the AI because basically it will
be important to see the differences.
OK, so if I go to my codecs.
There we are. This is.
The.
My conversation.
OK.
And here as you can see inside the eye,
I already have the proposed changes
within the editor.
So that's something you have to get used
to,
because that's that has become the normal
way of doing this.
This kind of development, OK.
Right. And at some point, not, not today,
we will dedicate sometime also in.
I will show you a full code browsing
session using the eye OK because it's
something that you have to get familiar
with because now also.
Google released the AI studio anthropic
release the their own version,
open AI release.
The Visual Studio code plug in to to do
codecs inside Visual Studio code.
So that's becoming the norm.
OK.
Right. So.
You were mentioning stash.
Why are you using the stash?
And.
They're not really dead,
and so I just asked them. I used to.
And what happens to this?
That should change. Yeah,
it's really with a little start where you
can both and and they are just,
they're waiting for you to stop the line.
It couldn't back to the action box with
the there is change.
Basically stashes.
Small assignments use the IM study about
the stash operation.
Conceptually stashes I'd like to
basically freeze these changes that I
made because I need the the clean
repository that because I need to do some
operation because there are some.
Operation that are impossible if you have
changes to the the current branch.
So you want to suspend those changes.
Basically, no,
you want to go and do something else and
go back and restore them.
So it's like having a stack of changes
that I want to suspend and then restore.
Lots of people I know they stash and they
never retrieve.
They use it just as a way to remove
changes to the branch,
which of course works, but right?
So that's basically very quick overview
of the.
Of these tools and why this is important
because when you start browsing the code
of a real code base,
the most important parts are not only the
information that you will find inside of
the the source files, but also.
The comments, the dates,
so if you if you see the I see I'm
browsing the core Clr which is the
runtime the.net runtime source code.
And you see the latest.
Pull Request accepted and then you say
last commit message end date for each and
every elements.
And of course you can see that there are
part.
Five years ago.
It it is a code that is there since.
I'm not. I won't say from the beginning,
but almost OK.
And so the information about the change
helps you a lot to understand the core
things, active things etcetera,
etcetera and and comments are important.
Because they helps you to understand what
was the change that have been made.
The last changes made of course.
Then you can go and and see the pull
request or to see the story of the single
file to see all the evolution since the
beginning.
OK, that's all possible, but nevertheless,
let's not go to that level of.
So how did I find this?
Usually you have to you you browse and go
on GitHub.
Most of the source code is available on
GitHub GitHub. There are few other.
Repository code repository repositories
worldwide available,
but GitHub is still the the the most big
one. It has been acquired by Microsoft.
Say six or seven years ago.
So basically it is owned by Microsoft.
It provides essentially a free service.
The only thing you have to pay is if you
want nowadays AI.
Related services. Then you have to pay.
Otherwise you can use it freely also for
creating private repositories.
So service communication.
Unfortunately we I signed an agreement
with GitHub a few years ago for the
enterprise.
Level.
Suddenly they discontinued this and then
I reapply and they said you're welcome to
the enterprise level and that's OK.
But you didn't give me,
I'm sorry to inform you that it was a
joke. I mean,
so actually we are not having copilot.
So please stop me.
And asking a copilot licence because we
have to pay, we don't have money, so it's,
I can tell you use the free version and
free here is not perfect but it works OK.
So.
net is 1 organisation and and it is
maintained by the NET Foundation which is
an open foundation which is supervised
the evolutionofthe.net framework.
As you can see,
there are areas in which the organisation
being important repositories,
because of course there are a lot of
repositories in this thing and of course
in ASP in.net you you find the runtime.
The Roslyn is basically the platform
which is used to create the compilers.
Actually when we browse the C# compiler I
was browsing the Roslyn.
Asp.net Core,
which is the web framework which is very
popular waveforms, is an old framework.
Then of course there are documents and.
Umm.
And others. So if you look.
The University of Pisa,
you will find that there is the simu 5G,
which is an open source simulator system
that has been developed by engineers and
it's being used by Intel and many other
big corporation as part of.
The development,
as you can see it's A and then there are.
Few other repos from a survey I did.
I think we are the most active university
having repository public on guitar but
with open source that is not just the I
am source code and I committed I mean
that that's not open source.
That's just you release the SUS code. OK,
so runtime looks like.
The interesting place to to go to
understand the the the runtime.
Umm.
Of course, with the gate.
Sees them a number of tools that have
been developed around the geek system. OK,
so when you?
Go.
You will find the number of badges and
everything.
You can some you can automate a number of
processes,
unit testing how many of you have.
Created unit test or know what they are
OK?
And fewer than just using git.
Long story short,
unit test is creating small applications
that test single functionality in
software and then use a tool.
That runs all the tests and gives you a
beautiful report. OK?
And it will be nice to be able to run
tests after any changes,
so you are able to see.
The you're you're see,
you're able to see whether there are
obvious errors,
unit tests that are not enough to get rid
of errors. Another quick story.
Have you ever got in Windows?
The question will you wanna send the
feedback to Microsoft when an application
crashes?
Why, in your opinion,
I mean that if it's a Microsoft
application, you may say, OK,
it's windows,
it's natural that Microsoft asked me to
send the feedback to Microsoft,
but why should I send?
Umm.
The information to Microsoft,
if it's Adobe or some other application.
So actually it the nice it was 2008.
And Microsoft was having a problem that.
Any bug seem like a bug of the operating
system,
even if it was not OK because windows is
a rather open platform in not in terms of
the source code,
but of who can write drivers or elements
etcetera.
And so they were full of drivers that
kept crashing the operating system,
but it wasn't operating system fault.
It was fault of the drivers.
So they started a number of actions to
try to reduce these.
Perception that the operating system was
faulty,
while it in fact it was not the operating
system but components, external,
exterminated a lot,
and then they they thought that it was
would have been a good idea.
Because if you have a a bug in Adobe.
It's.
Difficult that you write to Adobe and
Adobe will fix the bike for you.
Unless you're a very big customer. OK,
so they said. OK, as a Microsoft,
we see all the crashes,
we get all the reports.
We builds internal statistics and all the.
Very common crashes from all the users
over all over the world.
We collect them and then we call Adobe.
If I hey,
Adobe has a big problem because this
crash is happening million times.
You have to work on that. OK,
that was the the original reason.
The second reason that is I think even
more interesting is that they have steel
today.
And if they are not the only one internal
statistics.
That estimate the likelihood that by
fixing a bug in the in in the code base,
you will introduce a new another bug.
In the small code base that I I developed,
after five years,
I wasn't sure that the changes I was
about to make was reasonable or not
because the risk is that you don't.
Remember all the assumption you made in
that particular thing,
and so you may break the the code base
and unit test. We all know they're good,
but they're not complete in spotting
these these things and so.
So internally they know that they have
all the statistics, commits,
bugs etcetera and so they they have an
estimate,
let's say 20% or 2% probability to
introduce a new bug by fixing another bug.
OK.
Now they started asking the question,
is it worth fixing a bug?
Because if a bug is rare enough?
Maybe a good idea and don't fix it
because we may create more problems than
the the problem we fix. OK,
so that's the reason because you got that
that thing.
So in very large code bases you have to
consider also this kind of phenomenon
over time and and and therefore browsing.
The code base becomes something that is
liking a treasure.
Finding a search for the treasure.
And.
And of course the automation mechanics
try to reduce as much as possible the
likeliness to introduce bug in in the
repo. OK, and so there are.
Agents that now automatically check out
the repo bills run the tests and and even
try to fix bugs. Let me see if there are.
You know, I think I have pizza pizza.
Or a column.
There we are.
So I'm getting a lot of pull requests
made by agents by both by the AI. OK,
so there are boats that go around and say
OK.
The mermaid has moved from 10.
9 zero to 1094.
Wanna upgrade it OK.
And so yes or no, and these are.
But they did. They did. I did match this.
I think as you can see,
there are a lot of automated pull request
generated and in general if I go and look
for the pull request,
this is compatibility.
I give in. For me,
I I get information about the
compatibility of this. So say OK,
if this is the dependable so it cheques
for dependencies changes and so I say.
From 1311 to 1520 compatibility 78%
should I merge want to take the risk or
you want to stay safe and don't touch?
And and then of course I can go and look
at the proposal changes there are.
Cheques that have been made automatically,
so there are no conflicts in this thing,
and so I may say, OK,
merge and I accept the merge. OK,
so as you can see the tool set now that
we have these tools such as git.
To manage and.
Manipulate the source not just as a bunch
of text files,
but a more organic tree like structure
that is made of text files brought to a
lot of tools that automatically.
Keeps changing. They they they work.
OK, so now that.
All these clearly the bigger the project,
the more appreciated is OK and there are
conventions such as source is where
typical you find the source code of
something so runtime source hopefully
will be.
The runtime source code,
not always this happen,
so don't be too optimistic,
but if you're lucky enough,
at least that then.
The the first browsing typically involves.
Looking at the names and trying to guess
from the names, a reasonable construction.
So there are things that you may know
core Clr.
You may know that Clr stands for stands
for common language runtime,
which is the name of the virtual machine.
The net virtual machine.
So of course Clr likely will contain the
virtual machine code.
Mono for all people that mono was the
open source implementationof.netbefore.
net became open source,
and so you will find interesting part
coming from the mono.
Legacy tests and tools and tasks you may
easily guess libraries you open and you
find that there are all.
The library set.
That you have in in a project like this.
So I mean if you wanna see system.
System IO.
Zip compression.
You go there and you find the source code
of the system IO compression and so you
can see how the zip file zip is
implemented. Zip is implemented and so on.
OK, so that's.
Easy enough, OK?
So.
Corsilla is.
You do the same.
You start looking around,
you hope to see some greet me.
Sorry in a very large code base you won't
find. Let me.
It may cost you six months of work only
just to understand the code base. OK,
so don't.
Think that this is an easy job so and my
goal in these three classes is to see how
a real virtual machine is implemented.
This is a production 1,
so it's interesting.
How a number of techniques,
which include both garbage collection,
so the ability to garbage collect
generated code at runtime by the runtime
itself, which is a.
Fairly interesting technique can be
implemented in terms of high level object
that were discussed until now, types,
type system etcetera.
And you will learn how the understanding
of the type system is essential to
understand the source code of the virtual
machine.
But we also take you put the chance to
learn how to browse browse something so
complicated. OK,
so let's have a first look.
None.
So there are DLLS.
Are dynamic linking libraries what are
dynamic linking libraries?
So.
Phoenix and Windows users dot SO or DLL.
What are?
Maybe friends is that they can be shared
with problems.
Yes, basically it's correct.
So when you develop very large project is
unlikely that you have all the source
code. You will use libraries,
libraries are basically.
Pre compiled piece of code and if we stay
on the system level so let's say C.
You will have all in.
See everything is a function.
You can't have nested functions.
So a library basically is a set of
functions and you have a table.
Inside this the the binary that which
says this function this address.
Yeah.
Once you have the library,
the linker which is part of the compiler
is responsible to resolve all the symbols
compiles,
so you get all the fragments and then you
have to put everything together into a
single executor.
By attaching calls from one binary model
to the other binary model.
So when you compile GCC,
you get obj files, which are basically.
Compiled modules that have not yet been
linked with the remaining libraries,
and that's basically the libraries and
typically you can statically link the
libraries.
So literally I want to copy paste the the
this library,
that library etcetera into a single
executable.
All the libraries are internal to this
executable.
That's the easy.
What are the potential disadvantages of
statically linking?
Bye brisa.
So first of all,
if I want to update then I have to update
the to recompile to recreate and this is
clearly one. So if I have 10 programmes.
On my file system,
all of them are using the C runtime which
is aligned. How many copy.
Copies of the C runtime will I have in in
my system.
Then if you statically compile you are
occupying more space.
Because for every programme using a very
common library you will get a copy of the
library inside the the the executable.
Of course the linker is not stupid.
The linker typically copies only those
portions of the file.
That would be of the library that would
be used.
So if part of the library is not used and
will not be linked OK.
But nevertheless, it will cost today.
Probably we will be happy we have enough
space to not go and statically link in
the 90s when our drives can be 50
megabytes. I can tell you space was.
The most important aspect to think about.
And so being able to share a library.
In the first place was a good thing
because you were saving space.
So you have the dynamically linked
libraries which are basically same thing,
but the library is loaded at the
dynamically at runtime and it's not
linked statically inside the executable.
Let me see if now GPT improves back and
show diagram.
That.
Exemplify DLS and linking.
Now what is the problem?
So in a binary file,
how do you think you invoke?
You end up invoking a function.
So what is the instruction in the
assembly code that will be generating
when invoke a function?
Call to the name. The name is assembly,
but then in machine languages.
The address and where this address is
based in relatively inside the executable
file. OK so.
When you statically link a file,
that's easy because you statically know
the address of the function that you are
linking. So the linker.
Basically there's all this fixing because.
Every module in the compilation as a
table import and export.
Export is the list of file of addresses
of the function contained in the module.
Any import are the list of function that
are required by that module.
So when the linker starts.
Looks for the old incoming,
computes the actual address of the module,
and then back patch the code so that you
get the actual address. That's easy.
Now when you go and do.
The dynamic linking actually you are
having this.
Basically architecture this basic
architecture.
So the code of the library the DLL is
shared by two programmes.
But of course.
Now the address of the programme,
the the address of the function is not
anymore the same for the two programmes
because they have different layouts,
they have different bytes internally.
So how can we fix that?
Yes and no. The the, the,
the the quickest.
So yeah you so when you use a dynamic
library,
typically you have a static library.
So that for you as a programmer you don't
have to know.
All the details of the invocation. OK,
so in this sense, yes.
But what happens under the hood is.
You simply have a table.
The table contains the pointer to the
function of the dynamic link in library.
So basically whenever you invoke in your
code. So if Programme 1 invokes.
The function full basically goes into a
table which is.
Available in the process user in the
process space which gives you the actual
address of that particular entry point.
You jump, you call to that. OK,
so basically dynamic linking libraries
are.
I mean to share the address from
different address spaces.
No, this one last thing.
This works thanks to the operating system.
Because the library will be loaded into
the memory of multiple processes and of
course also the memory is not infinite,
not only the fight system,
even worse than anything.
You don't want to load too many times.
Library dot dot DNA, so you don't want.
You do want not only that both processes
can share the library,
but also that in memory the library is
exactly the same.
How can you mean?
Any ideas?
So what is the one of the essential
functions of the operating system?
People.
And meet your man, OK?
If your memory means that every process
believes to have a flat under space,
wonderful.
But the truth is that then you produce is
a wall map to the actual pages where the
information is stored. OK,
Victor memory is.
A core man is one of the operating system.
Now if you have the,
the and how it is implemented that there
are there is support at the CPU level.
There are data structure that are called
page table entries PT ES.
There are also the PTD's that are page
table directory which basically associate
into special data structure the process
address to the real memory page. OK.
Now, because you have this mechanism,
you can make part of the memory of of two
different process to be in fact shared,
even though they are mapping into
different different spaces. OK,
because you take.
The the the the memory pages
corresponding to the virtual pages and
you make them pointing to the same
physical memory location or and this can
be but that will be expensive or you can
say.
I've got an idea.
Actually,
this idea was from Microsoft and the
Linux copy that if you want to know the
full story.
We are. Let me talk in terms of 32 bits,
which is easy.
I have 4 gigabyte so the process can
write only the 1st 2 gigabytes from 2
gigabytes to 4 gigabytes of memory that's
read all.
And so all the processes see the same
memory because it's read only.
So there's no way to corrupt those pages.
And you guess what?
All the dynamic libraries are mapped into
into the same addresses in all the
processes.
And we simplify a little bit the
implementation,
so DLLS are a crucial mechanism that
makes the software works, and it's also.
Terrible because most of the it's the
main reason why our system keeps crashing
today after update,
because of course it's difficult to
ensure that when I updated library DLL.
Programme one and Programme 2 will be OK
with the new version of the LED,
so dynamic linking has become one of the
most important mechanisms of modern
operating systems.
But at the same time it's also.
Point of which is very, very,
very important. And as you can see,
you have to understand also these
mechanics if you want to really
understand the programming because as we
would see.
One of the big contribution of javaand.
net was to make standard the dynamic
loading in Java.
You can add classes to that will be
loaded by an an existing.
A running programme without even stopping
the process and that running port
programme will be can be able to load the
code that was not even there when you
started the programme and of net the same
OK so.
The ability of dynamically linking and
loading is a core mechanics that has been
used by modern runtime quite a lot to
work and to give you features that you
can perceive at the programming language
level.
That otherwise won't be there.
So all these things are intertwined,
one with each other and and so you have
all the time you must be able to look at
all the stack to fully understand what's
going on in your programme otherwise.
You've not not separate time programme.
See you on Wednesday.
I.